Inventory of the Ward W. Husted papers, 1928-1980
University of Wyoming. American Heritage Center.
Ward W. Husted papers
1928-1980
Husted, Ward W., 1895-1986
04896
2.23 cubic ft. (4 document boxes, 1 slim document box, 1 F21 box)
University of Wyoming. American Heritage Center.
The Ward W. Husted papers largely contain materials concerning his twenty-year involvement in the Navajo Tribal Utility Authority.
Biography of Ward W. Husted
Ward Walker Husted was born June 20, 1895, in Galesburg, Illinois. He graduated from Lombard College in Galesburg in 1917. After serving in the aviation section of the U.S. Signal Corps during World War I, Husted moved to St. Joseph, Missouri, to begin his career in the gas industry. In 1929, he moved to Laramie, Wyoming, to manage the Laramie Gas Company. While in Laramie, Husted involved himself in numerous community service organizations including the Booster Club, the Jesters, the American Legion, and the Elks Club. He received the Laramie Daily Boomerang-Laramie Lions Club Community Service Award in 1959. Husted brought the first natural gas pipeline to Laramie in 1933. He was also a member of the Navajo Tribal Utility Authority in the 1970s, which encouraged his interest in Navajo life and history. During the Lincoln and Douglas Debates Centennial and Carl Sandburg Celebration, Husted returned to Galesburg to participate in the events. He died 2 September 1986.
Scope and Content
The Ward W. Husted papers largely contain materials concerning his twenty-year involvement in the Navajo Tribal Utility Authority (NTUA). This portion of the collection includes reports and minutes of the NTUA board of directors and correspondence concerning its actions. Husted also collected material on other Navajo economic developments. Other gas industry related material includes newsletters of the St. Joseph Gas Company from the time Husted was employed there along with miscellaneous reports and articles.
Local history is documented by Husted’s club memberships and by the articles he collected. Husted helped organize the Laramie Booster Club, a division of the Chamber of Commerce. He was also a member of the Jesters, a drama club. Playbills, scripts, and newspaper articles about the performances are included in the collection. Husted supported the University of Wyoming, especially the construction of the Arena Auditorium. Probably due to his participation in the NTUA, Husted collected information about the Navajo tribe. Also of interest to Husted was the Lincoln and Douglas Debate Centennial and Carl Sandburg Celebration in his hometown of Galesburg, Illinois. He saved brochures, newspapers, and correspondence concerning the events.
Some photographs of Husted and the NTUA board are found in the collection. Several artifacts, including honorary medals from the NTUA, press passbooks to the World’s Fair in 1939, a gasoline ration book from World War II, and other Wyoming souvenirs are also included.
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions on the materials for research purposes, and the collection is open to the public.
Related Materials
There are no other known archival collections created by Ward W. Husted at the date of processing.
Acquisition Information
The Ward W. Husted papers were given to the AHC by Husted’s daughter, Jean Husted Hager in April 1987. The material was received in good condition.
Access Terms
Sandburg, Carl, 1878-1967.; Newcomen Society of the United States.; University of Wyoming--History.; University of Wyoming--Sports.; Jesters Club (Laramie, Wyo.); Laramie Booster Club.; Navajo Indians.; Gas companies--Wyoming--Laramie.; Lincoln-Douglas debates, 1858.; Galesburg (Ill.); Saint Joseph (Mo.); Laramie (Wyo.); Wyoming--History--1919-1945.; Wyoming--History--1946-; Scrapbooks.; Public utilities Employees.;; NTUA (Tribal utility authority).; St. Joseph Gas Company.
Wyoming; Education; Colleges and Universities; People, Ethnicity, and Culture; Native Americans; Politics, Government, and Law; Public Utilities; Business, Industry, Labor, and Commerce; Transportation; Science, Technology and Health; Energy Production
Container List
- Gas Industry Material, 1924-1984; Series I.; (31 folders)
  Reports, newsletters, correspondence, minutes, and articles relating to the gas industry.
  - Navajo Tribal Utility Authority, 1966-1984; Subseries 1.
    Arranged alphabetically by format. Reports, correspondence, minutes and articles.
    - Annual Reports, 1966, 1974, 1975, 1976, 1980, 1983 (Box 1, Folders 1-2)
    - Correspondence, December 1973-July 1975 (Box 1, Folders 3-4)
    - History, 1968, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Loan Contract-REA Project, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Manuals, 1973, 1982, undated (Box 1, Folders 7-9)
    - Minutes and Reports, June 1973-October 1974 (Box 2, Folders 1-7)
    - Miscellaneous, 1978, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1974, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Pamphlets, 1973, 1974, 1980, undated (Box 2, Folders 10-11)
    - Pamphlets and Brochures, 1973, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Reports, 1972, 1975, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Travel Reports, 1966-1974 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Reports, 1924-1963; Subseries 2.
    Arranged chronologically. Reports concerning practices and procedures in the manufacturing of gas.
    - Bituminous Coal Operation in 11ft. W.G. Sections, 1924 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Use of Soft Coal as Generator Fuel, 1926 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Committee on the Use of bituminous Coal as Generator Fuel, 1927 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Reports from R.W. Beck and Associates, 1962-1963 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous, 1925-1974; Subseries 3.
    Arranged alphabetically by title. Articles, newsletters, and booklets relating to the gas industry.
    - Ohio Oil Company, 1943, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 8)
      In Memoriam and The Beacon
    - Marathon Oil Company, August 1972, February 1974 (Box 3, Folder 9)
      Marathon Messenger
    - St. Joseph Oil Company, 1925-1928 (Box 3, Folder 10)
      The Illuminator
    - Story of Gas, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Historical Material, 1929-1982; Series II.; (19 folders)
  Arranged alphabetically by subject. Articles, correspondence, pamphlets, brochures, and magazines of historical interest.
  - Lincoln and Douglas Debate and Carl Sandburg Celebration, 1958-1978; Subseries 1.
    Articles, correspondence, and programs.
    - Carl Sandburg Biographical Information, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Carl Sandburg Celebration Program, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Carl Sandburg Centenary, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Knox College Publications, 1958, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      Alumnus and Knox Now
    - Lincoln and Douglas Debate Centennial Souvenir Program, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Newspaper Clippings and Magazine Articles, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Navajo Tribal Information, 1968-1975; Subseries 2.
    Newspaper clippings, a book, and leaflets.
    - Navajo: A Century of Progress, 1868-1968 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      Edited by Martin A. Link
    - Newspaper Clippings and Magazine Articles, 1968-1975 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Pamphlets and Leaflets, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Wyoming Material, 1933-1982; Subseries 3.
    Articles, brochures, maps, and a telephone directory.
    - Douglas and Converse County, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Laramie Maps (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Laramie Newspaper Clippings, 1949-1979 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Laramie Telephone Directory, 1933-1934 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Literature; Short stories or histories of Wyoming’s past, 1959, 1967, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Travel Guides, undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - University of Wyoming Brochures, 1948, 1982, undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
      University publications including recruitment booklets, Arena Auditorium programs, and information for the community.
    - University of Wyoming Newspaper Clippings, 1956, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - St. Joseph, Missouri, 1929; Subseries 4.
    A telephone directory.
    - Telephone Directory, 1929 (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Community Service Clubs and Awards, 1928-1985; Series III.; (1 box)
  Arranged alphabetically by subject. Articles, correspondence, newspaper clippings, invitations, playbills, a scrapbook, and awards.
  - Booster Club, Laramie, 1929, undated (Box 5, Folders 1-2)
  - Booster Club, St. Joseph, Missouri, 1928 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Laramie Chamber of Commerce, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - The Jesters, 1922-1940 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    Newspaper clippings, playbills, and scripts
  - Newcomen Society, 1963, 1964, 1975 (Box 5, Folders 6-8)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1940, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Scrapbook, 1960 (Box 6)
    Distinguished Citizen of 1959 by the Laramie Lions Club and Laramie Daily Boomerang.
  - War Manpower Commission Award, 1945 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Wyoming Elks, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Photographs, undated; Series IV.; (1 folder)
  Arranged by format. Pictures of Husted and members of the NTUA board.
  - Photographs, undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
    Husted and members of the NTUA board.
- Artifacts, 1939-1946; Series V.; (1 box)
  Arranged alphabetically by format. Press pass, stamp, coin, tie clip, ration book, and deposit bag.
  - Bank of Laramie Deposit Bag, undated (Box 6)
  - Gasoline Ration Book, 1945-1946 (Box 6)
  - Navajo Tribal Centennial Coin, 1968 (Box 6)
  - Navajo Tribal Council Tie Clip, undated (Box 6)
  - Olsen and Johnson’s International Association of Merry Screwballs Certificate, undated (Box 6)
  - Pressbook for the New York World’s Fair, 1939 (Box 6)
  - Stamp: “It’s Really Great to Live in Wonderful Wyoming,”, undated (Box 6)